<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mcaneff | My Portfolio</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on mcaneff | My Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 13:48:35 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gas–Surface Interactions in Hypersonic Reentry (Rarefied Regime)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/05-gas-surface-interactions-in_a_rareified_regiem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 13:48:35 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/05-gas-surface-interactions-in_a_rareified_regiem/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At extreme altitudes—above 100 km and especially in low Earth orbit (~400 km)—Earth’s atmosphere becomes so rarefied that it can no longer be treated as a continuum. Instead, the behavior of gas transitions to what is known as free molecular flow. In this regime, individual gas molecules rarely collide with one another; instead, they interact almost exclusively with the surfaces they encounter, such as the heat shield of a re-entry capsule.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runge Kutta: The Workhorse Numerical Integratior for  Orbital Mechanics and More</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/03-runge-kutta-the-workhorse-numerical-integratior-for--orbital-mechanics-and-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 15:40:48 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/03-runge-kutta-the-workhorse-numerical-integratior-for--orbital-mechanics-and-more/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is my goal to teach you how this numerical integratior works and hopefully why its better than the classical Euler solver you might be useto&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Kepler to Cartesian – Converting Orbital Elements to Position and Velocity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/02-from-kepler-to-cartesian--converting-orbital-elements-to-position-and-velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:34:23 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/02-from-kepler-to-cartesian--converting-orbital-elements-to-position-and-velocity/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re just starting out in orbital mechanics, Keplerian elements can feel like the secret code of the cosmos: elegant, compact , they work! Six numbers that somehow capture the shape, tilt, and timing of the orbits&amp;rsquo;s path around the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get eccentricity - telling you how circular something is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inclination - saying what is its tilt
and then some of the less intuitive ones, like the Argument of Perigee, which simply tells you at what angle along the orbit the closest point (perigee) is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving Lambert’s Problem, Part I: Foundations Through Kepler and Geometry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/01-lamberts-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 23:56:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/01-lamberts-problem/</guid>
      
        <description>A clear and structured explanation of Lambert&#39;s Problem in orbital mechanics, focused on the underlying time and geometric constraints of orbital transfers.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 20:57:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Michael—an engineer and graduate student with a passion for aerospace and 3D design. I enjoy solving problems, whether through software development, mechanical design, or exploring orbital mechanics. My work and studies focus on understanding spacecraft technologies and their role in space exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I earned my bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Engineering Science with a focus on Computer Engineering from the University of Western Ontario and am currently pursuing a master&amp;rsquo;s in Aerospace Engineering at Sofia University. I also work at Cisco Systems, specializing in VoIP technologies and software development in C++ and Swift.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture On Lamberts Problem</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/04-lecture-on_lamberts-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 13:48:35 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/04-lecture-on_lamberts-problem/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post contains a lecture I delivered to my colleagues at Sofia University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the real-world applications of Lambert&amp;rsquo;s Problem in lunar and interplanetary transfers, I structured this material to cover both the theoretical foundations and the numerical methods required to solve it. The lecture includes derivations, Kepler’s equation extensions, historical context, and a practical implementation for an Earth-to-Moon mission using a ∆V-constrained trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-takeaways-from-the-lecture&#34;&gt;Key Takeaways from the Lecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full derivation of Lambert’s equation from geometric and anomaly-based methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical evolution: From Lambert and Lagrange to Gauss and modern numerical solvers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application: Transfer trajectory planning with ∆V constraints and lunar orbit targeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementation: Code-ready parameters modeled after Apollo mission architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools: Applied in FreeFlyer with contextual mission planning using a porkchop plot subset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lamberts-problem-lecture-pdf&#34;&gt;Lambert’s Problem Lecture PDF&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pdfs/Orbital Mechanics Lamberts Problem.pdf&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;800px&#34; style=&#34;border: none;&#34;&gt;
    This browser does not support PDFs. Please download the file instead:
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pdfs/Orbital_Mechanics_Lamberts_Problem.pdf&#34;&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>